Gerald A McCollam

SUMMARY

Software developer, data engineer, student, trainer and mentor. I have broad expertise in data management for machine learning, in distributed computing, image analysis, visualization, and in automation. I build and manage systems for analytics and discovery.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Lead Data Architect, Openmine LLC

January 2011 - Present

Openmine is a consultancy specializing in web and data services development. We design and deploy systems for automatic discovery, selection, aggregation and publication.

- Funded Two-year USDA grant, Determining Sucrose Yield in Sugar Cane by UAV Aerial Imaging, 2015-2017.
- Contract to build and maintain a data-processing system for image analytics, Neuro-Informatics Data Modeling for Connectomics, SCAN Lab, University of New Orleans and The Mind Research Network, Albuquerque, NM. (2016)

Solutions Architect, Bladelogic-BMC

July 2006 - February 2010

- Principal technical architect for clients Pfizer, Novartis, Merrill Lynch, and Vanguard.
- Technical Trainer for Client Solutions group.
- Contributor to multiple internal automation solutions.

Consulting Engineer, Hewlett-Packard Enterprise

January 2003 – June 2006

- Member of the Automated Operations Group (AOPS).
- Provided server, network and process-level automation systems to clients.
- Consulting Engineer to clients Time-Warner, Reuters, MSNBC, and Columbia University.

Consulting Engineer, Loudcloud

 $January\ 2001-June\ 2003$

- Company founded by Marc Andressen (Andressen-Horowitz, Netscape).
- Developed Opsware server provisioning and automation suite.
- Consulting Engineer to clients Estee-Lauder, Univision, and AT&T.

Technologist, Razorfish

September 1999 - January 2001

- Translated client requirements into deliverable and supportable web solutions.
- Organized and directed project teams.

EDUCATION

Candidate, Master of Science, Biostatistics Department of Computer Science and Department of Psychology University of New Orleans, New Orleans, LA THESIS - Generative Models of the Human Connectome GPA 3.90 May 2017

Bachelor of Applied Science, Cognitive Neuroscience New York University, New York, NY THESIS - Neural Correlates of the Language Acquisition Device. GPA 3.56

May 1997

SKILLS

Advanced:

• Application Architecture, API Development, Configuration Management, Data Center Operations, Data Management, Deployment Planning, GIS, Java, Linux, OS, NLP, Python, Shell Scripting, SQL, Web Development, Release Management, Web Services Architecture.

Intermediate:

 Amazon Web Services (AWS), Cluster Computing, Core.NET, Dev/Ops, Git, Hadoop, HDFS, HTML5, Javascript, JSON, MapReduce, MongoDB, Neo4j, OpenGeo, OpenLayers, PostGIS, PostgreSQL, Statistics.

Acquired:

• Aerial imaging, AngularJS, ArcGIS, Computer Vision (CV), Cypher, Dronekit API, Pix4D, R, SciPy Stack, UAVs.

AWARDS AND CERTIFICATIONS

Founders Day Award, New York University, 1997.
Cloudera Certified Developer for Hadoop (CCDH), 2014.
OpenGeo GeoServer Certified Developer, 2015.
USDA/SARE 2 Year Study Grant Award, 2015-2017, FS14-282.
Jason Stamps Memorial Scholarship Award, University of New Orleans, 2016.

INTERESTS

Guitarist, luthier, painter, certified Yoga instructor, cook.